Leah: Quite a lot of the time the focus
of effective teamwork relates to have good
working relationships with other members
of the team and while this is critical
to the successful completion of projects,
what about relationships with other teams?
Chris: It is just as important to
develop good working relationships
with other teams as there are very few
instances when a project relies solely
on the input and output of one team.
To successfully complete a project
there will likely be several teams
working on different elements.
Leah: As we mentioned in session 1,
when working in an ‘Agile’ environment,
projects will involve teams with a
variety of skillsets who will work
on different elements of a project.
These teams will rely on each other as
the project progresses and frequently
use ‘Scrum’ and ‘Kanban’ methodologies
to track progress across the teams.
This enables the teams to
monitor progress and identify any
potential risks or holdups and
develop solutions to move forward.
Chris: Multi team projects can help
to maintain effective and develop
positive working relationships.
This way you can gain a holistic view of
the project and working with other teams
on collaborative projects are also a
useful way to gain an understanding about
the organisation’s other moving parts,
and how those parts can work together to
better achieve the organisation’s mission.
When members of different teams
communicate frequently, you should
always feel able to ask questions
and have a firm grasp of the nature
of one another’s work and therefore
productivity is considerably boosted.
Leah: Collaborative work also allows
team members to bring their individual
work styles, skills, and perspectives
to projects which creates opportunities
for new solutions and better results.
Imagine not knowing that the perfect
approach, team member, or resource
for a task your team is stuck on, has
been under your nose the entire time.
Chris: Good communication
provides opportunities to improve
your own teams’ methodologies.
When teams from different departments
are transparent about how they work,
it gives you the opportunity to
review the way you do your own work
which can highlight any weaknesses
that you or another team might have.
When working together, take note of
what questions others ask about your
department, what is confusing to them
about the way you do your work, and
consider how that might help you to find
ways to improve your own ways of working.
Leah: It can also help you to gain a
greater sense of the challenges that
might be faced in terms of deadlines and
discover ways you can continue to support
one another, coordinate your work with
each other, and provide support to others.